<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning from the Lord unto the rulers of Dover And so to all men which stand guilty of the like practises, that all may know a day of repentance before it be too late; for the night will come when as no man can work, in which the son of man will come as a thief unto all such the workers of iniquity, and give to every man according to his deeds done in their body in their life-time. Then wo to the eveil-doer, for it will go ill with him. Also, the Christian man's plea for his liberty, as he is so indeed and in truth: and also, as he is a free-born English-man, he lays claim to his birth-right, by way of expostulation with the rulers of Dover, who rob him and many others of it, refusing to shew us any order for their so doing. Together with a true testimony born to the Light of Jesus, the power of God, yea the power of the endless life, from everlasting to everlasting: by Luke Howard.</title>
            <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215380</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827274</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31691</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31691)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1890:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning from the Lord unto the rulers of Dover And so to all men which stand guilty of the like practises, that all may know a day of repentance before it be too late; for the night will come when as no man can work, in which the son of man will come as a thief unto all such the workers of iniquity, and give to every man according to his deeds done in their body in their life-time. Then wo to the eveil-doer, for it will go ill with him. Also, the Christian man's plea for his liberty, as he is so indeed and in truth: and also, as he is a free-born English-man, he lays claim to his birth-right, by way of expostulation with the rulers of Dover, who rob him and many others of it, refusing to shew us any order for their so doing. Together with a true testimony born to the Light of Jesus, the power of God, yea the power of the endless life, from everlasting to everlasting: by Luke Howard.</title>
                  <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Wilson, and are to be sold at the Black-spread-Eagle and Windmill in Martins l'Grand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31691:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING FROM THE LORD UNTO THE Rulers of Dover.</p>
            <p>And ſo to all men which ſtand guilty of the like Practiſes, that all may know a Day of Repentance before it be too late; for the Night will come whenas no man can work, in which the Son of man will come as a Thief unto all ſuch the Workers of Iniquity, and give to every man according to his deeds done in their body in their life-time.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Then wo to the Evil-doer, for it will go ill with him.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Alſo, the Chriſtian man's Plea for his Liberty, as he is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth: And alſo, as he is a free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man, he lays claim to his Birth-right, by way of Expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Rulers of <hi>DOVER,</hi> who rob him and many others of it, refuſing to ſhew us any Order for their ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Together with a true Teſtimony born to the Light of Jeſus, the Power of God, yea the Power of the endleſs Life, from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting to everlaſting: By <hi>LUKE HOWARD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 57.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The wicked are like the troubled Sea when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up Mire and Dirt.</p>
               <p>How ever it be, yet God is good, and his mercies are ſure to Iſrael, yea they endure for ever.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 24.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lay not wait, O wicked man, againſt the dwelling of the righteous, ſpoil not his reſting place.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 28.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoſo cauſeth the righteous to go aſtray in an evil way, he ſhall fall himſelf into his own pit; but the upright ſhall have good things in poſſeſſion.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 10.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſings are upon the head of the juſt; but violence cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the mouth of the wicked.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed For <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmill</hi> in <hi>Martins l'Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31691:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31691:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="warning">
            <pb facs="tcp:31691:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31691:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> VVarning from the Lord unto the Rulers of <hi>Dover,</hi> and ſo to all men men which ſtand guilty of the like Practiſes, that all may know a Day of Repentance before it be too late, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ON the third day of the 8th, Month, 1661. in the night-watch, upon my Bed of Straw and Chaff<note n="*" place="margin">Yet <hi>I</hi> and he reſt of my friends did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Marſhall to give him as we gave in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Priſons, <hi>8.</hi> pence a night for two Beds fitting for men to lye upon, and that our friends as in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, might come at us; but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it.</note>, in the Common-Goal of <hi>Dover</hi>-Caſtle; as I lay in a ſweet and a comfortable ſleep and reſt, the hand of my God fell on me, and his ſweet and comfortable preſence awaken'd me, and ſo continued with me unto the Morning-Watch; in which time the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preſence of my God was with me, and the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fellowſhip of his holy Spirit accompanied me, ſo that my ſoul was filled with his living preſence as with a mighty River, which did overflow the Banks, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appeared but joy and gladneſs, and the Streams of his everlaſting Vertue run through me exceeding ſwift, and as the dew from Heaven refreſheth the tender Graſs, ſo was the Plant of God's Renown refreſhed in me, and gave glory to him that ſitteth on the Throne, the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Days, and to the Lamb for evermore; even ſo faith my ſoul, and all that is within me; yea, praiſe ye the Lord, for he is worthy.</p>
            <p>And as I thus lay with my mind ſtaid on his Holineſs, and my heart awake in his Life and Light, the Word of his Eternal Power came to me, and from the God of Life
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31691:4"/>it run through me in theſe words, the which I was to write as from the God of my Life to the Rulers of <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Spoil, a Spoil, a Spoil is in you; a Spoil, a Spoil, a Spoil is in your hearts; yee blood-thirſty men, <hi>John Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Mayor, <hi>George West,</hi> and all which are agreed with you, whoſe hearts are filled with envy<note n="a" place="margin">Envy is the ground of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and it is murder in Gods ſight; as ſaith the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note>, to deſtroy a man and his Heritage, yea men and their Families, the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are againſt you, and the righteous venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Almighty is gathering together in his heart againſt you, and the Revelation thereof is near at hand to be poured forth: As your iniquities ripen to a head, and your envy againſt the righteous is fully accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, come you forth, and ſtand up before the righteous God of my Life, and let the God of Truth be judge in the matter, and his living Witneſs<note n="b" place="margin">For that wil plead the cauſe of the juſt and innocent, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, between God and your own conſciences</note> in all your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences give Anſwer between us, and this Word of Life run through my heart from the righteous God, to write unto you in the Word of the Lord, even the Lord God of Life and Light, of Righteouſneſs and Truth, the God of Heaven and Earth, whoſe dreadful preſence wil make the ſtrong to bow, and bring the lofty down, and rebuke the wicked devices of the heart of man, &amp; ſtrike through the Liver of the Oppreſſor, as with a Dart, and none ſhall ſhift his hand; before whoſe glorious preſence all muſt appear, and all fleſh muſt be ſilenced before him. This is my God, I have waited for him, and his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to me and mine is as as the Morning without clouds, and his beauty hath taken my heart, and his comelineſs hath raviſhed my ſoul, and his exceeding Riches hath he adorned my inward man with<note n="c" place="margin">The Kings Daughters are all glorious within.</note>, and his everlaſting ſtrength is my ſalvation, even the Son of his Love, which was from everlaſting to everlaſting, the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever, by whom he will judge the World in righteouſneſs, and the men thereof in truth, and no covering<note n="d" place="margin">VVo be to him who is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a covering, and not of the spirit of the Lord.</note> of falſhood ſhall then hide any, but all muſt ſtand naked and bare before him and his holy Angels, and mighty Hoſt of Redeemed ones,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31691:4"/>the hundred fourty and four thouſand<note n="e" place="margin">Then ſhall the Lord be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in his Saints, honored in his choſen, and glorified in and among his people, his own.</note>, which he hath redeemed from the Earth, who ſhall ſit upon the holy Hill of <hi>Sion</hi> with new Songs in their mouths, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Praiſes in their hearts, which hath followed the Lamb whereſoever he hath gone, and have not loved their lives unto death. Theſe are the generation of the Juſt, yea the general Aſſembly of the firſt born, whoſe names are written in Heaven. The Juſt men whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are made perfect, being waſhed in the blood of the Lamb, yea the Lamb of God that hath taken away their ſins, and carried them into the Land of forgetfulneſs, ſo that they ſhall never be remembred more againſt them. A new ſong of Salvation is put into their mouths, and joy and gladneſs is in their ſouls, and everlaſting praiſes is under their tongues, and the voice of Melody is in their inward parts, and the voice or ſhout of a King is in the midſt of them for evermore; ſo that great is the ſhout of the living Hoſt, which giveth all our glory and praiſes unto the Ancient of Dayes, and to the Lamb that lives for evermore; even ſo <hi>Amen, Amen</hi> ſaith my ſoul, and my Spirit ſets to its ſeal in the preſence of my God, who is the everlaſting Father, and Prince of Peace, of whoſe Dominion and Government there ſhall never be an end, but he ſhall reign for evermore; before whoſe ſeat of Juſtice<note n="f" place="margin">Where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wil ſpeak peace but a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence both to God and man, and no cover hide but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life which hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome death in all it covers.</note>, and Tribunal of everlaſting Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (I ſay again, all muſt ſtand naked and bare, and no covering ſhall be able to hide the leaſt Iniquity; but Judgement from the righteous God muſt come on all; and I ſay again, all fleſh muſt and ſhall be ſilent in his preſence, and all tongues confeſs to his righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and all knees bend before him, and all hearts fail in his preſence; for ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth the righteous, and true altogether is the Lamb that paſſeth ſentence, which ſaith, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting torments, prepared for the Devil and his Angels for ever; and come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the World; for I was a hungry, and ye fed me; I was ſick, and ye viſited me; I was in Priſon, and ye came unto me,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31691:5"/>and you ſhall not loſe your</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">The Lord taketh notice of all mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and will aſſuredly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all men accordingly.</note> 
               <hi>Reward, that have given but a Cup of cold water to a Diſciple in the Name of a Diſciple; foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ye did it unto one of the little ones which believed in my Name, ye did it unto me: Come ye bleſſed of my Father, enter into reſt, and partake of my everlaſting Life and Love, for ever and for ever, world without end. And go ye curſed</hi> (you that have caſt into holes and Priſons) <hi>into endleſs pains, wo and miſery, for ever and for ever, world without end;</hi> for you have been ſo far from viſiting me in my Lambs and Babes, and little ones in priſons, that you have caſt them in, and blaſphemed my holy Name, my Power in them, calling it the power of the Devil, and Deluſion, (to wit)<note n="h" place="margin">This is the condemnation of the world, that Light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil.</note> my Light which they make mention of, and ſpeaking all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil againſt them falſly for my Names ſake, and have made lyes your refuge, and under falſhood have hid your ſelves among men like unto yourſelves; to bring your wicked purpoſes to paſs againſt my holy Nation, and choſen people; for though in your Envy you have falſly charged them, and by ſo doing, evil entreated them; yet what have you found againſt them juſtly, to deſerve ſuch uſage from you as they have had? Yea, are they not clear and innocent? Have not you ſearched them again and again, &amp; proved them again and again, and ſtill what have you found? Even nought in them; but a lying heart<note n="i" place="margin">Through the whole Nation, how often even over and ever, have they been falſly charged, and ſo much ſearched &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day can yet be proved, becauſe they are clear in all matters.</note> in your ſelves, and the deceit thereof hath turned you aſide, ſo that juſtice hath been turned backward, and Equity hath fallen in the ſtreet, &amp; Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath ſtood afar off, and Truth it could not enter; becauſe <hi>the beſt of you have been as a bryar, and the moſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteſt of you ſharper then a Thorn-Hedge; yea, your Mercies have been but Cruelties to them; for he that departed from iniquity, you made a prey upon, and eat his fleſh as a man ſhould eat bread, and took not pity upon the needy, but ſtrengthened the hands of the</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">This is the portion of the ſervants of the Lord in this world, from the men thereof.</note> 
               <hi>wicked, to turn him out of the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath been your carriage and behaviour towards me in them, O ye ſtrong Okes and tall Cedars, whoſe tops I will lop off, yea and whoſe root I will pluck up, for the evil you have acted againſt me in my ſervants in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31691:5"/>your life-time, when you ſhould have feared my Name, and have met often together with thoſe which did meet, to wait upon me, and call upon my Name, which is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Righteouſneſs and Truth, Life and Light, which whoſoever walketh therein, walketh ſafely, and is free from harm in a ſtrong Tower of Defence; but on the contrary, you have broke up their Meetings, and ſent them to Priſons, and caſt them in holes, and all hath been for obeying me, and walking in my Light (your condemnation) and aſſembling<note n="l" place="margin">They which feared the Lord in the dayes paſt met often toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; <hi>a</hi> Book of remembrance was written, and ſo it is now</note> themſelves together in my fear, to wait upon me, to receive of my fulneſs, Life and Love, and to walk therein; yea to their and my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as is fully made manifeſt to ſuch which have ſought by the Power of Darkneſs, to rout out my Name, and cauſe it to be forgotten among the Sons of Men, among whom I will be glorified, by ſetting of it up, ſaith the jealous God; for I will march through you, O you bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars and thorns<note n="m" place="margin">Wicked men are unto the Lord as bryars and thorns are unto the fire, &amp; conſumed muſt they be if they repent not.</note>, and will burn you together, and ſet up my Name of Everlaſting Righteouſneſs; for by it am I known to my choſen, and ſo muſt I be to the ſons of men for evermore: And this is the Name by which they ſhall know me, and by which they ſhall call me, <hi>the Lord our Righteouſneſs;</hi> for I will be glorified in them, and they ſhall ſanctifie me in their hearts<note n="n" place="margin">The true iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God, their fear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God is not taught by the Precepts of man, neither do they fear him, but the Lord, though they be accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter for it.</note>, and make me their fear &amp; their dread (and not man) as my Flock of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath done in the day of their afflictions, when the wicked have made long furrows on their backs, and accounted them as ſheep for the ſlaughter, even all the day long. Ah! ſhal I not viſit for theſe things? Yea aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and my hand ſhall be avenged on their oppreſſors; for Vengeance is in my heart, and the day of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence is in my reins, and everlaſting contempt is in my bowels, and I am filled therewith, and I muſt be eaſed, and that on my Adverſaries, my Flock-oppreſſors, that have ſet themſelves againſt me, to deſtroy my Heritage, and ſcatter the ſheep of my Paſture, and have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make them forget their reſting-place in me, ſo that they ſhould not ſanctifie me in their hearts, and make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31691:6"/>me their fear and their dread; but would have them fear man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, who I ſtrike down in my own time, &amp; he is<note n="o" place="margin">All power is in the hand of the Lord; therefor ſhould men fear him, and take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him ly his witneſs in them, that they ſin not againſt him, not afflict his people if they love their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal peace.</note> no more; therefore be ye fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, O mortal men, and touch not my annointed ones, and do my Prophets no harm; if you wil have me to ſay to you at your end, Come ye bleſſed, enter into your Maſters joy, and ſit down at my right hand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of my Love, Life and Joy for evermore, with which I ſatisfie every hungry and thirſty ſoul in his life-time; by which refreſhments my ſervants, my ſons and my daughters have bore forth their Teſtimony unto my Life, Power and Love, the which I have ſhed abroad in their hearts, and thereby have ſtood over the Power of Hell and of Death, and have given their bodies, goods and lives, a witneſs for me; the which I will own even for ever, and it ſtands upon everlaſting Record in my Book of Life, never to be blotted out; for time ſhall ceaſe, and Seaſons have an end, and man whoſe life is there (to wit) in Times and Seaſons, ſhall periſh therein, and his Name ſhall rot; but my Choſen ſhall remain on Record in Life everlaſting. The Mouth of the living God hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall ſurely be fulfilled, and the eyes of my He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage ſhall ſee it, and I will be glorified in and amongſt them for ever and for ever; and all ſorrow and ſighing ſhall be wiped away from off them, and nothing be heard<note n="p" place="margin">The life of the righteous is a life of joy, &amp; it ſhall be for ever, world without end.</note> but joy and gladneſs, melody and praiſes on the ten-ſtringed Inſtruments, Hallelujahs for ever and for ever. Then will I be known in the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to be Head of my Family, and Ruler over my Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; yea when my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, and their Enemies languiſh for ſorrow of heart, and pain of ſpirit<note n="q" place="margin">The torment of the wicked is great &amp; endleſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Men plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Miniſters and their glory muſt fall before the glory of the Lord.</note>, and anguiſh of Reins, yea then will I be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted among the holy Nation, and ſet up among the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prieſthood; and then ſhall the Deceivers faces wax pale, and the falſe Prophets Spirit ſink into the Pit, and the Diviner be made mad, and all <hi>r</hi> which have leaned on them [and not repented] go down with them into the Lake: and then bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31691:6"/>for theirs is the Kingdom of God for ever and ever; and this is the portion of the Heritage of God, and their lot for ever, ſaith the righteous God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who never ſlumbers nor ſleepes, but will perform his promiſe<note n="s" place="margin">Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is the ground of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving hope in God, of the truth of it: I am a witneſs for the Lord.</note> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his Covenant to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and not fail in one tittle, ſaith the Lord of Hoſt, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe Promiſe is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> to Ages and Generations, yea for ever and for ever. So be it ſaith my ſoul, whom the Lord hath reared up in his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love &amp; Power, to be a witneſs of his Name amongſt crooked &amp; a perverſe generation, yea a ſeed of evil-doers, &amp; children of falſhood, that are ready to lay and ſay all maner of evil againſt me for righteouſnes ſake, but falſly.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay again, Come forth, and ſtand upon the Tryal before my Father, the righteous God of my Life; &amp; you workers of Iniquity, <hi>John Golder, George Weſt,</hi> and all which ſtand by you in your evil Cauſe; I ſay, let us reaſon together, and let God's Witneſs in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences be judge between us in the cauſe; for that is my friend<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> believed in God and it was rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and he was called the friend of God; and he which is Chriſts, is <hi>Abraham's</hi> Seed, and heirs according to promiſe, who hath crucified the fleſh, with the luſt and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo is the friend of God.</note>, and will plead my cauſe when you are on your Beds, in the Morning-Watch, in ſecret it ſpeaks, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies the innocent, and now let it be judge between us in this matter (to wit) our Right and Priviledges, as we are men created of God, to live on the face of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Are you born Chriſtians, as men account you? And free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men? So am I. Are you entitled to live in the Nation of <hi>England?</hi> So am I. Are you Free-Men of <hi>Dover</hi> Town? So am I. Have you never forfeited your Freedom? Neither have I. Have you ſerved the Town in Offices? So have I. Have you lived in good faſhion, even honeſtly in the Town? So have I. Have you kept men and maid-ſervants? So have I. Have you Families of W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe and Children? So have I. Have you provided for them in honeſty by your own Labours, without defrand and guile? So have I. Have you kept out of all mens Debts, and danger of being caſt into priſon therefore? So have I. Can you ſay you ſpend not the Creation of God upon your Luſt? So can I. Can you ſay you are no drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31691:7"/>nor Bowlers, nor Evil-livers? ſo can I. Can you ſay ſuch you were, but you are waſhed, but you are ſanctified? ſo can I. Can you ſay you once lived in pleaſure, even wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly on the earth, ſpending your days out of God's fear, &amp; ſo crucifying the Juſt, as ſaith the Scripture? ſo can I. Can you ſay you have known a day (from the Lord) of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and bitterneſs of ſoul for it? ſo can I. Can you ſay you have hearkened to the Spirit of Truth which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the world of ſin and all ungodlineſs? ſo can I. Can you ſay you have believed in the Light which maketh all things manifeſt that ever you have done againſt God? ſo can I. Can you ſay you have known repentance from dead works, both in converſation and worſhip, to ſerve the living God in newneſs of life? ſo can I. Can you ſay you have known the reproof of Inſtruction to be the way of life? ſo can I. Can you ſay the Judgements of the Lord are ſweeter to you then the honey and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-comb; for by them you have learned obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life? ſo can I. Can you ſay you love the Lord your God (that created you) with all your ſouls, with all your minds, with all your ſtrength, and your neighbours as your ſelves? ſo can I. Can you ſay you can forſake Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Wife and Children, Houſe and Land, and Gold, for his Name ſake that is the Light of the World? ſo can I. Can you ſay you can take it patiently, and rejoice that you are counted worthy to ſuffer, and to have your Trades ſpoiled, and your Families expoſed to hardſhip for Chriſt's ſake? ſo can I. Can you give your backs to the ſmiter, and your cheeks to him which pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth off the hairs, for a good Conſcience-ſake? ſo can I. Can you dwel in a Priſon all dayes of your lives, rather then ſin againſt the God of Righteouſneſs? ſo can I? Are you true Chriſtians in Nature, and not in Name onely, which can do good againſt evil, and ſeek to overcome evil therewith? ſo can I. Can you bleſs them that curſe you, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the words of Chriſt, and ſo render not evil for evil? ſo can I. Can you in ſuch a caſe of Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31691:7"/>your cauſe to the righteous God? ſo can I. Can you as true Chriſtians, bear your Teſtimony againſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Conſcience-ſake? ſo can I. Can you uſe all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means to keep ſuch out of Priſon, who for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake cannot follow the multitude to do wickedly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? ſo can I. Can you deny your ſelves ſo far, as to viſit them that are caſt in for Conſcience-ſake? ſo can I. Can you read and believe that Scripture which ſaith, <hi>The Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon</hi> (to wit, the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Jeſus) <hi>and you ſhall have tribulations ten days?</hi> ſo can I. Can you beſieve the Scripture which ſaith, <hi>Foraſmuch as you did it to the leaſt of thoſe which believe in my Name, you did it unto me?</hi> ſo can I. Can you believe that the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſs of God is his Name, &amp; that it is known in his Light which ſhineth in mans heart, to give him the light of the knowledg of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Scriptures? ſo can I. Can you believe that they which rebel againſt the Light of God nor the conſcience, never know the way of true peace in the path thereof? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which walketh in the Light, as he is in the Light, hath fellowſhip with God, and one with another? ſo can I. Can you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he which hateth the Light, bringeth not his deeds unto it, leſt it ſhould reprove him? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which loveth the Light, bringeth his deeds to it willingly, that he may know they are wrought in God? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an evil device in his heart againſt his Neighbor, hates the Light which ſhines therein, and ſins againſt God, and is in danger of his curſe? ſo can <hi>I.</hi> Can you believe that for every idle word that man ſhall ſpeak, he muſt give an account in the day of God's righteous Judgements, and for every vain thought, and all his deeds done in his body, whether they be good, or whether they be evil? ſo can <hi>I.</hi> Can you believe that no Drunkard, nor Lyar, nor Fornicator, nor Adulterer, nor Idolater, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankind, and ſuch like, ſhall never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God? ſo can I. Can you believe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31691:8"/>that man ought to deny himſelf of all theſe things, and to obey the Spirit of Light which ſhews and reproves for theſe things in ſecret, or elſe he is no Chriſtian in nature, but in name onely? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which doth not fear God, and hate covetouſneſs, and ſo in God's fear knows how to rule his own body and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, is not fit to rule amongſt men? ſo can I. Can you believe that he w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> doth not love the Light w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhines in his heart, nor yeilds obedience to it, ſo that he may know the power of the endleſs life, that ſuch a man who is a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, &amp; hates the Light, may turn the Sword of Power upon the back of the righteous, and ſo ſin againſt God? ſo can I. Can you believe, that he which is not firſt ruled himſelf by the power of God in his own heart, can never rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for God? ſo can I Can you believe that every man which in that ſtate takes the ſtaff of Juſtice to ſway withall, hath cauſe to take ſhame to himſelf, and give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and ſo repent? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which rules amongſt men ſhould be juſt, and judge every one's cauſe without reſpect of perſons, and upbraid none? ſo can I. Can you believe that he that ſets upon the ſeat of Juſtice, and upbraideth any man, or paſſeth Judgement with reſpect of perſons to any man, that ſuch a man doth greatly ſin againſt God, whoſe place (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men) he ſitteth in, and that his evil is exceeding great? ſo can I. Can you believe that the Rulers of Towns and Cities have a great weight and burthen to bear, as from God, when they join with the rude people, which hate in their heart a righteous government, and ſo ſet themſelves to ſuppreſs ſuch as love Righteouſneſs and its government, againſt the evil-doers? ſo can I. Can you believe that the Law was not made for the righteous man (to wit, that Law which is holy, juſt and good) but for the lawleſs and diſobedient (to wit) for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, Swearers, Drunkards, Lyars, Revellers, and ſuch like? ſo can I. Can you believe that if any man ſuffer as a Chriſtirn for well-doing, he hath cauſe to glorifie God on that behalf? ſo can I. Can you believe that he which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31691:8"/>believeth all theſe things, and walketh in his duty to the Lord, is a true Chriſtian, and a true Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that ſo rules over men, and no otherwiſe? So can I<note n="u" place="margin">All this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth, and to the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in every man's Conſcience, to which <hi>I</hi> do make my appeal, and let that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as <hi>I</hi> know it will, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, when the mind is ſtill and quiet.</note>.</p>
            <p>And then if theſe things be by me conſented to, and believed and practiſed as well in my place, then you do in your places, then come and let my friend in your own boſomes, the living Witneſs of the Lord, ſpeak if I have not as much right both by the Law of God and Nature, to enjoy my Liberty of Body and Conſcience, as your ſelves; and if you do ſtand and abide in this Faith of a true Chriſtians life, then whether ſuch as can perſecute for conſcience-ſake, are not altogether out of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans life, and ſo enemies to the croſs of Jeſus, as I and you have been in the dayes paſt; and for you which have had a hand in it, (to wit, in perſecution) to deny your ſelves, and to take ſhame to your ſelves, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and all men, is but your duty unto the Lord, and confeſs and give glory to God, and ſay, the time paſt may ſuffice you to have wrought the will of the Gentiles or Heathens in perſecuting the Seed of God in the Chriſtians, and now will I repent and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor (as juſt cauſe there is) my ſelf in duſt and aſhes, and make it my buſineſs (ſo far as I can) to redeem the time, and take off the heavy burdens, and ſet the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed free, by undoing every heavy yoke and unrighteous Decree which my hand hath been ſet to, and help to lay on; for in this am I now ſatisfied, and that from the Lord, by his Witneſs<note n="x" place="margin">Gods wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience teacheth all to deny themſelves in evil, that loves it, and is led by it, to wit, the Light.</note> in my own conſcience, that he which doth not do even to all, as he would have another to do to him, is no Chriſtian in nature, whatſoever he is in name, neither can he fulfil the Law of God, which is to love our enemies, and alſo our neighbours as our ſelves; and unto this ſtate of life muſt all men come that ever know true peace with the Lord; and he which is not here, is out of the life which all the holy men of God were in, in all ages paſt, and is under the curſe, as ſaith the Law, and denies the Faith, the power of God, as ſaith
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31691:9"/>the Goſpel of Peace, and ſo is a ſervant to the power of darkneſs, which rules as Lord in the hearts of all men which hateth the Light which ſhineth therein, to ſhew them the deſperate wickedneſs thereof; for all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs proceedeth out of the<note n="y" place="margin">The heart of man is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeat of all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, whileſt he hateth the light which ſhineth therein</note> evil and wickedneſs of the heart, the ſeat thereof; and the pure Light of Jeſus, the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, ſhineth therein alſo, as ſaith the Scripture, for to make it manifeſt to man's clear underſtanding, unto which all men ſhall one day confeſs to the glory of God; and that is God's everlaſting love even to all men which do receive it in the love of it, and that is the Grace of God which appears to all men, yea the ſame Grace which bringeth ſalvation even to as many as believe in it; for he which believeth in the Light wherewith he is in his heart lighted, ſhall not abide in the darkneſſe which firſt ruled in his heart, and is made manifeſt by the Light, but he ſhall have the light of life, yea the ſame Life which gives him power over thoſe deeds of darkneſs and evil which the Light makes manifeſt to his clear underſtanding to be evil; ſo that he which doth well, and takes good heed to the Light in his own heart, ſhall have little need to ask another what is good, and what is evil, hee may know it plain enough in his own Conſcience, by the Light, as he watcheth to it; and this is the ſame Grace which the Lord unto <hi>Paul</hi> (in his doubting eſtate) gave his full Teſtimony unto, ſaying, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> found<note n="z" place="margin">He which receives the grace of God, the light which ſhines in his heart, in the love of it grows into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord, which is life eternal, and to the fulfilling of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> it ſo to be, and teſtifies to it, ſaying. <hi>By the grace of God I am what</hi> I <hi>am:</hi> And he gives forth the ſame Teſtimony of its bringing ſalvation, in his Letter to <hi>Titus,</hi> in theſe words, ſaying, <hi>The Grace of God which bringeth ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us</hi> [Mark that] <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſt, and to live ſoberly and godly in this preſent world.</hi> So that this is a true Teſtimony by the Spirit of the Lord, born unto all men, that all which loveth it as it ſhines in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31691:9"/>heart, from the Lord, the Fountain of Life and Light, they are taught by it to deny all ungodlineſs, as <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Chriſtians in their dayes were; and all which hates it, are not taught by it, neither can they receive it whileſt they hate it; for no man's heart can be joined to the thing which in his heart he hates; but firſt man muſt feel a ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of love to the thing he receives, and ſomething muſt appear to him to beget his love to ſpring: Now Light in it ſelf is lovely<note n="a" place="margin">All men muſt love the thing they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, aright; therefore love the Light aright, that you may know its vertue which is life.</note> to the eye which can behold it; now the eye which can behold the Light of the glorious Goſpel, the God of this World hath blinded, or the power of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hath ſtole away the affections of the heart from the Creator, who is Light, ſo darkneſs comes to rule (as God) in the heart: Now that which ſometimes even (as it were) darts into man's heart in ſecret, that is Light and Love, from the God of Light and Love; and as this is taken heed unto, the power is felt which reacheth unto the ſeed of God, which witneſſes to the truth which the Light and Love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in the heart; ſo then a ſpringing begins to be felt from the Seed of God towards the Light and Love, which is in it ſelf of a begetting nature, and then as the Light is ſtill taken heed unto, the ſpringing of the love of the Seed encreaſes; ſo the eye comes to be open which can ſee a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Light, that it ſhould be deſired, for Light is love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in it ſelf; and ſtill as the Light is taken heed unto, the love of the Seed encreaſes; &amp; as the love encreaſes<note n="b" place="margin">This is a true growing from one degree of Grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in the Lord, who is that Spirit; and as he comes to rule in the heart, ſo comes liberty.</note> ſtrength and power is felt to ſtand over that which the Light ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth manifeſt to be evil; and as a meaſure of power is felt to deny ſome evil which the Light reproves, then the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkneſs appears to make war againſt the Power of the Light; and this is the true warfare between the fleſh and the ſpirit; and in this ſtate moſt men cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am!</hi> becauſe ſin now appears out of meaſure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; yea that which man formerly thought to be no ſin, he now ſees to be great; and ſo the ground of ſin appears, and the whole body of iniquity ſtands up, with which he is now to make war in righteouſneſs; and now he ſeeth his ſtrength, though it be but ſmall, to ſtand wholly in the light
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31691:10"/>and love, which hath begun the Work in the Spirit, to war againſt the fleſh. And this is the time to wait on the Lord<note n="c" place="margin">He which waiteth on the Lord ſhall not be aſhamed, but ſhall renew his ſtrength in the Lord dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note> to feel the living hope to ſpring; yea the exſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Seed which loves the Light, to receive power in the Light from the Fountain of Life, to overccome the whole Body of Death; and he that hath this hope, purifieth himſelf as God is pure; and although he meet with many encounters with the power of darkneſs, yet the hope ſtands faſt in God, the Fountain of Life and Light, from whom he daily expecteth a ſupply of ſtrength to deny the evil, and ſo he feels the body of ſin to weaken, and this is true purifying of the heart by faith, and theſe experiences come to be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed of God's power, &amp; the hope is confirmed, which makes not aſhamed, but the ſhame of the daily croſs begins now to flee away, and here is ſtrength in God known, now to take up the Croſs, and deſpiſe the ſhame; and now the Croſs is known and felt to be the power of God, which cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies to the world, and the affections that have been in it, and after it, they now are felt to be wounded<note n="d" place="margin">Here the Scripture comes to be fulfilled.</note>, and the hope ſtand faſt ſtill, as the Anchor of the ſoul unto God, that in due time the body of death ſhall be ſlain; and now comes the watching to the light (againſt fainting) to be known; for ſtill the enemy will ſeek to perſwade the mind againſt overcoming<note n="e" place="margin">VVhich is the doctrine of the Devil and his Miniſters.</note>, ſaying in the heart, <hi>The time is long, and the work is tedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, and thy ſtreights are many, and ſtrength is ſmall, and how ſhalt thou get through? will he in the heart be ready to ſay,</hi> when the watch to the light is neglected; for then is his time to work<note n="f" place="margin">The Lord ſows the good ſeed of his word in the field of the world, which is in mans heart, as ſaith the Scripture; and whileſt man ſleeps, the evil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſons ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es.</note> in the darkneſs or night whilſt man neglects to watch, and ſo ſleeps. Therefore I ſay, watch ye to the light, and when temptations comes in, yea great and many, look not at all at them, but look to the light which makes them manifeſt, and watch to the power, to withſtand them, and ſo the Seed which at the firſt loved the light, will now feel its ſtrength encreaſe, and its power abound over the temptation; and here is the Victory, even that which overcomes, felt and witneſſed, and now the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant fruits of Righteouſneſs comes to be brought forth, and the fruits of the obedience of the Spirit, which are joy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31691:10"/>and peace, and now a meaſure of conquering comes to be witneſſed through Jeſus Chriſt, the Light of men, and the Power of God, by whoſe Blood and Life Victory is witneſſed; and now all ſelf-righteouſneſs, &amp; ſelf-ſtrength or power, is denied, and the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, the Power of God<note n="g" place="margin">The Lord is the ſtrength of the righteous, its he which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all our works for us, and in us.</note>, alone given glory unto, and honor and everlaſting thankſgiving, for ever and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; for he is worthy, who is the Light that was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the work, and is the Life and Power of God to bring to the end, and accompliſh the work over the power of Hell, and the Body of Death, and ſo to give entrance into the Reſt which remains for the people of God, through believing in him that is the Light and Power of God, to ſave from all, which by his Light he condemns; and now comes the peace to be felt which paſſeth the underſtanding of all which rebel againſt the Light which ſhines in the heart, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, the which all know and feel which live in the faith which gives the Victory, and keeps in the ſame, and ſerves the Lord in the newneſs of the Spirit, and not in the oldneſs of the Letter, which the firſt Nature can make a profeſſion of in the enmity, as <hi>Cain</hi> the <hi>firſt-born</hi> could do, yea offer outward Sacrifices, with that heart and mind which he could murder his Brother in, which many can do now, even profeſs God, and Chriſt, and Scripture, and yet live Enemies to the life of God, and Chriſt, and Scripture, and Croſs, and ſo in <hi>Cain</hi>'s na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note n="h" place="margin">And muſt have <hi>Cains</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond from God, and ſo marked until repentance be witneſſed.</note>, are ſeldom but <hi>angry</hi> with ſuch as live in the faith, by which <hi>Abel</hi> offered a more acceptable Sacrifice then <hi>Cain</hi> did. And when the power of their anger moves in them, then are ready to murder as he he did, and even deſire in their envious hearts for a Law to do it by; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſhamed, and alſo afraid of their own lives, to do it without. But let all ſuch know, and that from the living God, that they ſtand as <hi>Murderers</hi> in the account of God<note n="i" place="margin">For he which in his heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, is a mans ſlayer.</note>, and that this is true of that Spirit which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31691:11"/>live but in ſin, and yet will cover it over with a profeſſion, in the oldneſs of the Letter. You may take a view of <hi>New-England,</hi> which have drunk ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much of the Blood of the <hi>Faithful</hi> of late days; and in <hi>Old-England</hi> too, many thirſt after it, and are in the plain ſteps for it, to caſt the faithful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Holes</hi> and <hi>Priſons,</hi> as they do, boaſting in the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> of their hearts, of a Law (before it be made) of <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> after much other cruelty is uſed, and caſt into Priſons before-hand, as if it were to be ready for it; but this is our <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Confidence,</hi> that we know in whom we have believed, even in him by whom Kings <hi>reign,</hi> and Princes <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree Juſtice;</hi> and for ſuch as will decree <hi>unjuſtice</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> by Law, we fear<note n="k" place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, our Example, our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, our Fore-runner, our elder Brother, was put to death by a Law, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps, ſaying, if they did ſo to the green tree, what will they do unto the dry? But remember what befel them; and alſo whether ſuch can eſcape which do it to his Members and Body, the Church, which is, in God the Father, whereof Chriſt the Light is the Head. So in this be ye all warned.</note> them not, but ſhall commit our <hi>Righteous Cauſe</hi> to the God of our Life; the God of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and let him plead it for us, which I am aſſured of, will be too ſtrong for his and his people Enemies in the end; and this is the <hi>Counſel</hi> he hath given us, (and wee have taken it, bleſſed be his Name for ever) not to fear man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, but to fear the Lord alone, and to ſanctifie him in our hearts, and to make him <hi>our fear,</hi> and <hi>our dread,</hi> for evermore: Even ſo be it, ſaith the hearts of all the faithful ones, the <hi>Heritage</hi> of God, and <hi>ſheep</hi> of his Paſture, and <hi>Lambs</hi> of his Fold, and <hi>Labourers</hi> in his Vinyard and Garden, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he is come to ear his pleaſant fruits, and to walk amongſt his Lillyes, Praiſes, Praiſes be unto him for evermore; yea everlaſting glory, be unto the ancient of dayes, our God, and our Father, from everlaſting to everlaſting, even ſo Amen, ſaith all the upright in heart, for ever and for ever.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:31691:11"/>
            <p>And thus have I cleared my Conſcience in faithfulneſs to God and man, as the Lord put it into my heart, and moved me to declare it in writing from the place of my abode, for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience unto God, in the Houſe of Cruelty in <hi>Dover-Caſtle</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Goal, but a place of Comfort and great Joy unto us, in and from the Lord, whoſe Mercies and loving-kindneſſes I hope and pray may never fail unto me his ſervant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>LUKE HOWARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="paper">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:31691:12"/>
            <head>Here is alſo a ſmall <hi>Paper,</hi> the which a Neceſsity fell upon me to write, for the clearing of my Conſcience in the Matter it ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of.</head>
            <p>THis is in my Heart, to clear my Conſcience (that the Guilty may bear their own Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then) unto all ſober-minded-people, which have not given over themſelves to work wickedneſs with greedineſs, and cannot join themſelves with ſuch, againſt the Righteous God and his peaceable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to deſtroy them and their Families, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting them of providing for them by their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in which they are willing to abide, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lord, to work and get their own Bread, their Wives and Childrens, and to be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to others, which by reaſon of Age, Sickneſs, or Lameneſs, are not able to help themſelves; And therefore,</p>
            <p>O you people of <hi>Dover,</hi> be yee my witneſses, that have known me from my Child-hood unto this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31691:12"/>day, that I have lived all along by the ſweat of my own face in honeſty, and therein <hi>I</hi> have, through God's bleſſing, provided for me and my Family, which the God of my Life hath ſet me as a Steward over.</p>
            <p>Therefore be yee my Witneſses in my laſt impriſonment in <hi>Dover</hi> for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, if I did not take all oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to labour and provide for my Family, according to my duty both to God and them; but it ſeemeth that was not puniſhment bad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (to bee hindered in part) in the eye of the angry-deſtroying Spirit, which ſeeks to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy honeſt men, their Wives and Children all at once; for <hi>John Golder</hi> the Town <hi>Mayor</hi> ſaid to us whom hee ſent for to his houſe (the twenty ſecond day of the ſeventh Month, 1661) in his angry threatning ſpirit, <hi>That wee ſhould not have ſuch impriſonment as wee had the laſt time;</hi> ſo it ſeems plain by him, hee thought it too good, and why, except it was becauſe we could work a little, to provide ſomething for our Families, after ſmall and low Rates, unto which it would be hard for him to come; but truth teacheth us to live ſo, and content to us is very precious.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is wrote to clear my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the ſight of God and man, that if I remain here under this Reſtraint, for ought I can ſee, or any man can ſhew me (and I have well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31691:13"/>of it) that my beſt way is to let my Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ceaſe from working; for if they continue working, and I continue in Priſon, as I am; that then my damage may be greater, then if they work not, as men of underſtanding in our Trade will confeſs, ſo for my men to forbear working, that muſt I chuſe, and that in obedience to the Lord, whoſe fear is before my eyes in it, and whoſe preſence is with me, and the Word of his Patience runneth through me, to bear all loſſes for his Name ſake with patience; in the feeling of which, I ſhall chuſe rather to part with all outward things, yea life it ſelf, then ſin againſt the God of my Life, whoſe love is great to me, unto whom I ſhall commit my cauſe, and the care of my Wife and little ones (who are dear and near to me) whoſe care I know is over all that put their truſt in him, and his juſt hand over their oppreſſors, to deal with them in due time, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they deal with others, to the fulfilling of the Scriptures of Truth, and ſo ſhall every man have from his juſt hand according to their deeds done in the body, whether good or evil; and then a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence to God and man, wil be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding precious; in which I reſt in peace and love to my Enemies, a Priſoner for Conſcience-ſake in the Houſe of Bondage, in <hi>Dover-Caſtle</hi> Common-gaol, but a Free man in the Lord in the freedom of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which is beſt of all, and more then all; Even ſo <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written</hi> 
                  <date>the 28. <hi>of the</hi> 7th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31691:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
